Guide to the James Roy Newman Papers, 1920-1966
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
James Roy Newman papers 1920-1966
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Newman, James Roy, 1907-1966
23.4 Linear Feet 9844 Items
Editor of the "New Republic" and "Scientific American."
Collection contains notebooks, correspondence, a large variety of writings, a diary, and some clippings. The correspondence largely involves his duties as editor but includes personal matters as well. Writings include entry lists for the HARPER ENCYCLOPEDIA OF SCIENCE, essays, typescripts, articles for THE WORLD OF MATHEMATICS, book drafts, manuscript of GÖDEL’S PROOF, and other scientific writings. There are a large number of book reviews and articles, including some on atomic energy. Two manuscripts were written by his wife, Ruth (Gallert) Newman and there is a term paper by his daughter.(93-187) The addition (8 volumes) contains notebooks that appear to hold notes from college courses. They include a transcribed lecture by Justice Felix Frankfurter. (00-265) The 3 volume addition comprises spiral-bound volumes of photocopied author catalog cards for items in this collection. (00-409)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The James Roy Newman Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1969.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Newman, James Roy, 1907-1966
Mathematics -- History
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1940-1963 and undated, (9 boxes)
  - 1947-1963 (Box 1)
  - A-G (Box 36)
  - H-Z (Box 37)
  - 1940-1947 (Box 38)
  - 1948-1950, June (Box 39)
  - 1950, July-1954 (Box 40)
  - 1955-1959, June (Box 41)
  - 1959, July-1960 and undated (Box 42)
  - Undated (Box 43)
- Subject Files Series, (2 boxes)
  - Subjects: A-F (Box 2)
  - Subjects: G-W
- Writings Series, (32 boxes)
  - Writings (Box 4-6)
  - Introduction and essays for The World of Mathematics (Box 7)
  - Harper's Encyclopedia of Science (Box 8)
  - Writings by Others (Box 9-10)
  - Mathematics notebooks (Box 11)
  - Writings (Box 12)
  - [BOX MISSING] (Box 13)
  - Writings (Box 14-16)
  - Treviso Arithmetic- What is science? (Box 17)
  - Writings (Box 18)
  - [BOX MISSING] (Box 19)
  - Book Reviews, 1940s-1950s (Box 20-24)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica (Box 27)
  - Harper's Encyclopedia of Science (Box 28)
  - Writings (Box 29)
  - Mathematics-Miscellaneous (Box 30)
  - World of Mathematics, (Volumes 1-3,5) (Box 31-34)
  - Writings (Box 34-35)
  - Wyckoff-Yale (Box 36)
  - Writings (Box 43)
- Printed Materials Series, (7 boxes)
  - Printed material (Box 15)
  - Clippings (Box 25)
  - Clippings: Einstein (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 44)
  - Volumes
  - Clippings
  - Clippings (Box 45)
  - Printed Material (Box 45-47)
- Ruth Gallert Newman Series, (9 boxes)
  - Correspondence (Box 48)
  - Subjects: A-C
  - Subjects: D-J (Box 49)
  - Subjects: K-P (Box 50)
  - Subjects: Q-S (Box 51)
  - Subjects: S-T (Box 52)
  - Subjects: U-Z (Box 53)
  - Miscellaneous
  - Pictures
  - Writings (Box 54-55)
  - Papers (Box 56)
  - Printed Material
- Accession 1993-187, 1924, (1 folder)
  Consists of one diary. Located at end of Box 56.
- Accession 2000-265, 1936-1937, (2 boxes)
  The addition (8 volumes) contains notebooks that appear to hold notes from college courses. They include a transcribed lecture by Justice Felix Frankfurter.
- Accession 2000-0409, (1 box)
  The 3 volume addition comprises of spiral-bound volumes of photocopied author catalog cards for items in this collection.